<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide link="doc/">
<title>Audio</title>
<author title="mean"><mail link="fixounet@free.fr">
	Mean</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Audio
 </abstract>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>08 Feb 2003</date>
<chapter>
<title>Process/Copy mode</title>
<section>
	<title>Copy mode</title>

	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>In that mode, avidemux will just copy the audio source (external/avi/...) to the output. It is used when you just cut an avi for example or change the audio track.That also applies to mpeg encoding/transcoding/requantizing.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Process mode</title>

	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>Avidemux will first decompress the audio, then apply the filters if any. If you don't set any filters, you will end up with a huge wav file as audio track.
	</p>
	<p>To be used,  the corresponding audio codec must be present on your system. See <uri link="input.xml.html">input format</uri>.
	</p>
	<p>When using <c>Audio->Save audio</c>, the audio is saved depending on the current mode. If the mode is set to copy, you will save a raw AC3/MP3/WMA... track. In process mode, the file will be processed then saved
	</p>
	<p>It can be useful to encode a track in MP2 to create a video CD for example. You will end up with a .m1v video elementary stream and a .mp2.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Filters</title>
<section>
	<title>Normalize</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>That filter normalize linearily the audio. It helps if the overall volume is very low (for example from ac3 audio track).
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Convert to 44.1 khz</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>That filter does the 48->44.1khz conversion. If the input is not 48 khz, it does nothing .
	</p>
	<p>It is based on wavefs44, borrowed from DVD2AVI.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Time shift</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter shifts the audio by removing the beginning or duplicating to create new sound. The value entered is the shift in ms.
	</p>
	<p>It is <b>the only filter to work also in copy mode</b>. Very handy to correct a sync error on avi or mpeg file.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Resample to </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter  resamples the audio to the user given frequency. It is faster than the 48->44.1 but may be of lower quality. It is based on a slightly modified sox engine.
	</p>	
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>

<section>
	<title>Pal2Film and Film2Pal </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>If you want to alter a video and change its fps from film (23.976) to pal (25) you have to use the film2pal filter on audio stream to keep audio/video sync. The opposite is true for pal to film encoding.
	</p>	
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Channels </title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>Allow you to switch from mono to stereo. It is sometimes needed as for example, mono audio is illegal for VCD.
			</p>	
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Encoder Filters</title>
<body>
<p>
These filters are just like regular filters, but they do output compressed audio.
</p><p>
</p>
</body>
<section>
	<title>Uncompressed</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>It does nothing and ouput the audio as PCM wav file. Handy to convert MP3->wave for example.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>MP3</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p> Based on liblame. You can select the bitrate and mode (joint stereo or stereo). For mono, it will be automatic.
	</p>
	<p> It encodes in CBR and VBR modes 
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Ffmpeg  mpeg audio</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This is lavcodec mpeg audio encoder.
	</p>
	<p>It encodes only in CBR mode (and no joint stereo, even if there is an entry in the dialog). It is declared suitable to use as DVD audio track.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Ffmpeg AC3</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>Also from libavcodec.
	</p>
	<p>It encodes stereo AC3 files. Never tried to see if the resulting AC3 is acceptable by an hardware decoder	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Toolame (internal)</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This is using a preversion of toolame that is a library and thus usable directly by avidemux without piping.
	</p>
	<p>From 2.0.24 and after, it is suitable to use as VCD/DVD audio track</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Use case</title>
<section>
	<title>Avi with WMA audio</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>Say you have an avi with WMA audio and want to convert it to MP3.
	</p>
	<p>Load your avi, let the video to copy as we won't modify it.
	</p>
	<p>Set the audio to process and select MP3 codec, <c>Audio->Audio codec</c>
	</p>
	<p>Select <c>Audio->configure codec</c>, set 128kbps j-stereo
	</p>
	<p><c>File->save avi</c>, and voila you just converted the audio track.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Avi with 44.1 Khz mp3 audio to DVD</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>In that case, we will select process mode, resample to 48 khz and ffmpeg mpeg audio.
	</p>
	<p>The audio track will be first decompressed to PCM, then upsampled to 48 Khz and finally compressed to mpeg audio
	</p>
	<p>You can then use <c>Audio-save audio</c> to get the .mp2 file, or use <c>File-Save as DVD PS</c> to directly save it as a mpeg containing both audio and video. This mpeg is suitable to dvd authoring directly.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
