<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide link="doc/">
<title>Video</title>
<author title="mean"><mail link="fixounet@free.fr">
	Mean</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Video : Interlacing filters
 </abstract>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>24 Apr 2005</date>

<chapter>
<title>Foreword</title>
<section>

	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter family deals with interlaced video.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Interlacing  filters</title>
<section>
	<title>Decomb telecide</title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>This is (yet another) port of <uri link="http://www.neuron2.net">Donal Graft</uri>. Its aim is to remove combing, including inverse telecine.
				Note that it does not alter framerate, and that you must use also
				<c>Decomb decimate</c> to do a proper IVTC.
			</p>
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Decomb decimate</title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>This is (yet another) port of <uri link="http://www.neuron2.net">Donal Graft</uri>. It removes frames according to several strategies. The most common usage is with telecide to do inverse telecide.
			</p>
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Pal Smart</title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>This filter is a mix between the two above. 
			</p>
			<p>It evals the current image and the Pal-shifted image, then takes the less interlaced one and smart deinterlace it. Since chroma is not taken into account, it can lead to small chroma error.
			</p>
			<p>It is a bit on the slow side, but very efficient when the video is of the good type.
			</p>
			<p>It can be used also as a cheap IVTC, as it will reconstruct the progressive frame, but will keep the video at 30 fps and will not discard duplicates to reach 24 fps.
			</p>
			
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Deinterlace</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter is a port of Donald Graft smart-deinterlace filter to YV12
	</p>
	<p>It detects if the image is interlaced and blurs the interlaced parts.
	</p>
	<p>This filter takes two parameters :
	<ul><li>Motion threshold : The lower this value, the more easily the interlacing will be detected. Too low means a lot of blurring !</li>
	<li>Blend threshold : When the video has been detected as interlaced, the parts that are under this threshold are blurred. It must be smaller than the previous threshold</li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Lavcodec PP  deinterlacer</title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>This filter is a port of lavcodec deinterlacer </p>
			<p>You can select :
				<ul>
					<li>Libear blend</li>
					<li>Linear interpolation</li>
					<li>Cubic interpolation</li>
					<li>Median interpolation</li>
					<li>FFmpeg deinterlacer</li>
				</ul>
			The best is to refer to mplayer/ffmpeg documentation for more details.
			</p>
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Pal Shift</title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>This filter  takes a field from an image and the other field from the next image.
			</p>
			<p>A lot of movie (and some DVD) are interlaced this way. 
			</p>
			<p>This filter does not do any check, so activate it, preview it, and if you are happy with the result keep it.
			</p>
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Drop</title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>This filter has been written by Ron Reithoffer.
			</p>
			<p>If a field is too different from spatial/temporal neighbours (VHS drop out) it is discarded and replaced by an average value from previous and next frame line.
			</p>
			<p>According to the author, this must be the first filter in the filter chain, and will not work well with very interlaced image.
			</p>
			<p><img src="../image_tuto/dropout.jpg"></img>
			</p>
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Kernel Deint</title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter is a port of Donald Graft kernel deint (avisynth), more stuff <uri link="http://www.neuron2.net">here</uri>.
	</p>
	<p>It is very efficient.
	</p>	
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>

</chapter>



<chapter>
<title>Fields related filters</title>
<section>
<title>Swap fields </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>It is very common that capture card/capture software swaps the fields. It will look like a interlacing effect, but on the whole image, not only on moving part</p>
	<p>
	This filter swaps the fields back. Here is a short example, first the image which has swapped fields :
	</p>
	<img src="../images/swap1.png"></img>
	<p>
		And the ouput of the Swap Fields filter :
	</p>
	<img src="../images/swap2.png"></img>

	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Smart Swap fields </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>It is also common that the capture card/software swaps fields back and forth several times. This filter tries to detect if the fields are swapped, and if so swaps them back.
	</p>
	<p>It is usually better to use this one, rather than the SwapFields filter.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Keep even field </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter will keep even field, i.e. even line numbers.</p>
	<p>It will halve the vertical resolution by 2</p> 
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Keep odd field </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>Same as above for odd field</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Separate Fields </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter will split a image in two images, each one receiving one of the field.
	</p>
	<p>So you will double the framerate, double the number of images, and halves vertical resolution.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Merge Fields </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>Opposite of above filter.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Stack Fields </title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>Each field is put on top of one another. Useful to see if some blending occured/if the fields are progressive.
			</p>
		<p>
			<img src="../images/stack.png"></img>
		</p>
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>UnStack Fields </title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>Opposite of previous filter.
			</p>
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
