<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide link="doc/">
<title>Video: Smoothing filters</title>
<author title="mean"><mail link="fixounet@free.fr">
	Mean</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Video: Smoothing filters
 </abstract>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>08 Feb 2003</date>
<chapter>
<title>Foreword</title>
<section>

	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter family smooths the video, very useful to get rid of the noise on captured source.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>

<title>Smoother filters</title>
<section>
	<title>Stabilize </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter replaces each pixel with the threshold by a weighted average of its spatial and temporal neightboors	</p>
	<p>It is a light denoiser.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Denoise </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter has been ported from transcode DNR filter</p>
	<p>It replaces each pixel with threshold of the reference by an average of reference and pixel</p>
	<p>It deals with luma and chroma with separate thresholds.</p>
	<p>It is a strong filter if you raise the default threshold values.</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>FluxSmooth </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter has been ported avisynth, and has been originally written by  Ross Thomas .</p> 
	<p>See avisynth doc to get more details </p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Temporal Cleaner </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter is originally from Jim Casaburi, part of virtual dub filters.</p> 
	<p> It has been ported from virtual dub to avisynth by Vlad59.</p> 
	<p>See virtual dub/avisynth doc to get more details </p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Mplayer Denoise3D </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter is a port of Mplayer Denoise3D filter, written by Daniel Moreno.</p> 
	<p> It is a very good denoiser.</p> 
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Mplayer HQDenoise3D </title>
	<body>
	<ul>
	<p>This filter is a port of Mplayer HQD3D filter, written by Daniel Moreno and A'rpi.</p> 
	<p> It is a very good denoiser, but its quality has a price :Two to three time slower than Denoise3D</p> 
	<p>You will probably be happy with Denoise3d.
	</p>
	</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Donald Graft's MSmooth  </title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>This filter is a port of Donald Graft MSmooth</p> 
			<p>It smooths the image while not blurring edges. Very usefull on animes.</p> 
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Forced PostProcessing </title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>This filter applies a blind postprocessing on the picture</p> 
			<p>The input number (quant) gives the strength the filter has, higher number means more postprocessing</p> 
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Soften</title>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<p>A variant of stabilize</p> 
		</ul>
	</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
